Simon Fraser collection
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
Simon Fraser collection
1803 - [ca. 2014]
F-208
Q105668872
19 cm of textual records 60 photographs 48 negatives 1 slide 2 drawings 4 artifacts 2 textiles
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
In 1976 a number of Fraser artifacts were formally transferred to the Vancouver Centennial Museum. These items (originally bequeathed to the University from the estate of Donald Fraser) included: one pair of sterling silver shoe buckles reported to have belonged to Simon Fraser, two embroideries done by Catherine Fraser (circa 1820), three silver teaspoons engraved "M.G.F.", one large sterling spoon engraved "M.G.F.", three silver plate tablespoons engraved "F.", two bisque figurines, and a medal dated 1908 struck at New Westminster Centennial celebration of the exploration of the Fraser River. An extended biography of Simon Fraser and a detailed content summary of the Simon Fraser Letters are included with the hard copy of the finding aid located in the SFU Archives reading room.
published
The title is based on the contents of the collection.
Collection consists of records relating to the personal history and genealogy of the university's namesake, the explorer, Simon Fraser. Records include; correspondence, working papers, reports, newsletters, newspaper clippings, photographs and negatives, drawings, artifacts and textiles.
Records have been arranged by the Archivist into subject-based series. Prior to arrangement, there was limited physical control over the textual and graphic artifacts because they had become integrated into the Archives reference files on the history and genealogy of Simon Fraser. These integrated files have been processed as found.
Archives and Records Management Department; Fraser, Simon; Lovat, Lord; Photographic materials; Artefacts; Graphic materials; Textual records; Exploration, discovery and travel
The SFU Archives Simon Fraser collection is an artificial collection compiled by Archives staff.
On September 9, 1965 the first artifacts were donated to Simon Fraser University by descendants of Simon Fraser and members of the Fraser Clan. Donald Fraser, a great-great grandson of Simon Fraser donated several manuscripts believed to be written by Simon Fraser, while Lord Lovat, Chief of the Fraser Clan, donated a ceremonial claymore (sword) and a jewel-encrusted powder horn.
Textual records on the subject of Fraser genealogy were donated to the Archives by Barbara Rogers while Fraser family photographs have been donated to the Archives by family members from across North America. Correspondence regarding the photographs can be found in Series 3.
Copies of textual records and photographs on the subject of Simon Fraser historic sites and family property were donated to the Archives by amateur historians J. Dennis Casey and Howard Wright of Hoosick Falls, NY.
For other material relating to Simon Fraser artifacts, see the finding aid to the Office of the President fonds (F-193), series 23-3.
Some of the files may contain personal or confidential information. Access to these files may be restricted as stipulated by Archives policy or the donor. Files marked 'pending review' must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release and, as a result of the review, access restrictions may apply. The original Simon Fraser letters are restricted because of their extremely fragile condition. However, digitized access copies are available. The genealogy file by Barbara Rogers may only be viewed with her permission. Please see the file and item lists, and consult the archivist for more details.
File and item lists are available.
- Simon Fraser history and SFU Archives correspondence, 1958 - [ca. 2014]; F-208-1; 16 cm of textual records 10 photographs
  published
  Series consists of records relating to Simon Fraser and includes general biographical information, university correspondence with members of the Fraser family and Lord Lovat, archival responses to research inquiries, a scrapbook of Fraser family news clippings created by Donald Fraser, Barbara Rogers genealogical research, Vancouver Sun newspaper articles written by Stephen Hume, and Simon Fraser historic site and family property reference material collected by J. Dennis Casey and Howard Wright. Records include correspondence, working papers and research notes, a scrapbook, newspaper clippings, publications, and copies of maps and photographs.
  Textual records; Photographic materials
  - Simon Fraser correspondence, 1958 - 1996; F-208-1-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 208-1)
    Textual records
    Open
  - Simon Fraser biographical information, 1964 - 2006; F-208-1-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 208-1)
  - Simon Fraser's grave, 1964 - 1980; F-208-1-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 208-1)
  - Donald Fraser scrapbook, 1965; F-208-1-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 208-1)
  - Lord Lovat, 1965 - 1995; F-208-1-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 208-1)
    Restricted in part
  - Barbara Rogers - B.C. Genealogist articles on Simon Fraser, 1989 - 1993; F-208-1-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 208-1)
  - Barbara Rogers - Simon Fraser genealogy research, 1990; F-208-1-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 208-1)
  - Barbara Rogers - research notes and correspondence, 1990 - 1999; F-208-1-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 208-1)
  - Clan Fraser Society newsletters, 1992 - 1994; F-208-1-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 208-1)
  - Stephen Hume newspaper articles on Simon Fraser, vol. 1, 2006; F-208-1-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 208-1)
    Records were printed off of the Vancouver Sun website by the archivist.
  - Stephen Hume newspaper articles on Simon Fraser, vol. 2, 2006; F-208-1-0-0-11 (Newspaper box 208-6)
    Records were ordered by the archivist from the Vancouver Sun to be included in the archival collection in May 2006.
  - J. Dennis Casey and Howard Wright - reference material on Simon Fraser historic sites and family property, [ca. 2014]; F-208-1-0-0-12; Includes 10 photographs (Newspaper box 208-6)
    File contains copies of materials related to Simon Fraser and his family's property in Hoosick Falls, NY, and other historic sites connected to Fraser in Cornwall and Williamstown, ON.
    Wright, Howard; Casey, J. Dennis; Textual records; Photographic materials
    A list of file contents was created in consultation with the donors because the documents themselves are not identified in any way (source or place). The file list is included on the file.
- Simon Fraser letters, 1803 - 1990; F-208-2; 2 cm of textual records; Conservation: in March 2006 a professional conservator assessed the conditions of the letters, and in January–February 2007 undertook conservation treatment. This involved cleaning the documents, removing tape carriers, and repairing tears. The conservator's report, as well as before and after photographs, are available in the Archives; consult the reference archivist for more information.
  The letters were donated to the university on opening day, September 9, 1965, by Donald Fraser, a great-grandson of Simon Fraser. However, the documents were misplaced and were found in 1988 in the desk belonging to a history professor. At this time, the University Archivist arranged to have a handwriting expert to analyze the documents and determine their authorship.
  Series consists of original letters written by Simon Fraser and supporting documentation. Series includes correspondence with Don Brown who was hired in 1988 to authenticate the letters, copies of other documents written by Simon Fraser from the National Archives of Canada that were used during the authentication process, and publicity regarding the identification of the letters. Records include correspondence, working papers, reports, and newspaper clippings.
  The original letters are restricted due to their fragile nature. Digitized access copies are available.
  For a detailed content summary of the Simon Fraser letters at the item level, please see Appendix 2 of the hard copy finding aid available in the Archives' Reading Room.
  - Genealogy of Ann Fraser McKenzie and the Frasers of Culbokie and Belladrum, 1846; F-208-2-0-0-0-1 (Newspaper box 208-7)
    Open: Digitized access copies
    Restricted in whole: Original, handwritten records
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item44. Creator's original file classification code: SF Letters 1.
  - Genealogy of Ann Fraser McKenzie and the Frasers of Culbokie and Belladrum, 1846; F-208-2-0-0-0-2 (Newspaper box 208-7)
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item45. Creator's original file classification code: SF Letters 2.
  - Genealogy of Culbokie family, 1846; F-208-2-0-0-0-3 (Newspaper box 208-7)
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item46. Creator's original file classification code: SF Letters 3.
  - Genealogy of Simon Fraser family, [18--]; F-208-2-0-0-0-4 (Newspaper box 208-7)
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item47. Creator's original file classification code: SF Letters 4.
  - Genealogy of Simon Fraser family - William, Simon, John, Archibald, Peter, Alex, Donald, James and Roderick Fraser, January 1846; F-208-2-0-0-0-5 (Newspaper box 208-7)
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item48. Creator's original file classification code: SF Letters 5.
  - Genealogy of Lord Fraser and descendants sharing William and Hugh Fraser names, Simon Fraser letter to John Fraser, 1846; F-208-2-0-0-0-6 (Newspaper box 208-7)
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item49. Creator's original file classification code: SF Letters 6.
  - Genealogy of William Mortay-Charse, Hugh and Ann Fraser, "Dear Brother" letter, [18--]; F-208-2-0-0-0-7 (Newspaper box 208-7)
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item50. Creator's original file classification code: SF Letters 7.
  - Genealogy of Angus, Margaret, William, Simon, John, Archibald, Peter, Alex, Donald, James, and Roderick Fraser, [18--]; F-208-2-0-0-0-8 (Newspaper box 208-7)
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item51. Creator's original file classification code: SF Letters 8.
  - Genealogy of Nancy Fraser and illegible (female) Fraser, [18--]; F-208-2-0-0-0-9 (Newspaper box 208-7)
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item52. Creator's original file classification code: SF Letters 9.
  - Genealogy of descendents sharing William and Hugh Fraser names, narrative "The antiquity of the Frasers", [18--]; F-208-2-0-0-0-10 (Newspaper box 208-7)
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item53. Creator's original file classification code: SF Letters 10.
  - Genealogy of the family of Glenmoriston, [18--]; F-208-2-0-0-0-11 (Newspaper box 208-7)
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item54. Creator's original file classification code: SF Letters 12.
  - Genealogy of Simon Fraser, Lord Lovat, [18--]; F-208-2-0-0-0-12 (Newspaper box 208-7)
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item55. Creator's original file classification code: SF Letters 13.
  - Equipment of Fort Liard, 1803; F-208-2-0-0-0-13 (Newspaper box 208-7)
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item56. Creator's original file classification code: SF Letters 14.
  - Genealogy of Lord Fraser and descendants sharing William and Hugh Fraser names, Simon Fraser letter to John Fraser, 1846; F-208-2-0-0-0-14 (Newspaper box 208-7)
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item57. Creator's original file classification code: SF Letters 24.
  - Handwriting analysis, 1988 - 1990; F-208-2-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 208-1)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1988 - 1989; F-208-2-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 208-1)
- Fraser family photographs, [18--] - 1996; F-208-3; 7 cm of textual records 50 photographs 48 negatives 1 slide
  Series consists of Fraser family photographs. Formats include original albumen photographs (i.e. photo cards), photographic prints and negatives. Photo subjects include family members, Simon Fraser's house, gravestone, and stained glass windows depicting the explorer.
  Negatives exist for most photographs and reference copies have been made from the albumen prints.
  Photographic materials
  - Photograph correspondence, 1965 - 1995; F-208-3-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 208-1)
  - Photographs - items 1-24, 43, [19--] - 1996; F-208-3-0-0-2 (Archival box - small 208-2)
    - House built by Simon Fraser, [19--]; F-208-3-0-0-2-1
      Photograph sent to SFU Archives by Donald G. Munro
      (ste. 720, 1350 Vidal Street, White Rock, BC V4B 5G6, phone: 535-1537).
      Black & white photograph depicts Catherine (Kinnear) Ginn sitting in chair in front of home that Simon Fraser built.
      Negative available in F-208-3-0-0-2.
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item1.
    - Donald Fraser at SFU opening ceremonies, September 1965; F-208-3-0-0-2-2
      Photograph sent to SFU Archives by Barbara Rogers on behalf of Joyce T. Burke (2014 Kilgore Road, Falls Church, VA 22043).
      Series of four (4) black & white photographs from SFU opending day ceremonies on September 9, 1965 attended by descendants of Simon Fraser.
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item2.
    - Mrs. Donald Fraser at SFU opening ceremonies, September 1965; F-208-3-0-0-2-3
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item3.
    - Lord Lovat and Donald Fraser at SFU opening ceremonies, September 1965; F-208-3-0-0-2-4
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item4.
    - Lord Lovat, Donald Fraser, and Mrs. Donald Fraser at SFU opening ceremonies, September 1965; F-208-3-0-0-2-5
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item5.
    - Mildred Tindall (Donald Fraser's sister), December 1955; F-208-3-0-0-2-6
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item6.
    - Simon Fraser's gravestone, 1995; F-208-3-0-0-2-7
      Photograph sent to SFU Archives by Aileen Britton
      (ste. 96, 27111 - 0 Avenue, Aldergrove, BC V4W 2T2).
      Colour photograph of Simon Fraser's gravestone.
      No negative for photograph.
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item7.
    - Kathleen (wife), Pamela (daughter) and Simon William Fraser, 1960; F-208-3-0-0-2-8
      Photograph sent to SFU Archives by Barbara Rogers on behalf of Irene Fraser (#4-736, N. Elm Street, Fargo, North Dakota 58102).
      Series of seven (7) black & white photographs of descendants of Simon Fraser.
      Negatives available in F-208-3-0-0-2.
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item8.
    - Robyn and Bruce Angus Fraser, 1966; F-208-3-0-0-2-9
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item9.
    - Donald Fraser, [19--]; F-208-3-0-0-2-10
      Note: photograph taken by Don E. Olson Studios, Fargo, North Dakota.
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item10.
    - Robin and Bruce Angus Fraser, 1991; F-208-3-0-0-2-11
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item11.
    - Marine Corp. Lieutenant Scott Simon Fraser and maternal grandfather, General Robert L. Scott, 1991; F-208-3-0-0-2-12
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item12.
    - Scott Simon Fraser, Robin (mother) and Robert L. Scott (maternal grandfather), 1991; F-208-3-0-0-2-13
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item13.
    - Bruce Angus Fraser and Laura (daughter), 1991; F-208-3-0-0-2-14
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item14.
    - Simon Fraser's grave, [199-?]; F-208-3-0-0-2-15
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item15.
    - Simon Fraser's grave, [199-?]; F-208-3-0-0-2-16
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item16.
    - Simon Fraser's grave, [199-?]; F-208-3-0-0-2-17
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item17.
    - Simon Fraser's grave, [199-?]; F-208-3-0-0-2-18
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item18.
    - Simon Fraser's grave with priest, [197-?]; F-208-3-0-0-2-19
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item19.
    - Simon Fraser's grave, [197-?]; F-208-3-0-0-2-20
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item20.
    - Simon Fraser portrait, [190-?]; F-208-3-0-0-2-21
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item21.
    - Mrs. Fraser portrait, [190-?]; F-208-3-0-0-2-22
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item22.
    - Simon Fraser - stained glass window, 1996; F-208-3-0-0-2-23
      Photo donated to SFU Archives by Barbara Rogers, 1996.
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item23.
    - Simon Fraser - stained glass window, detail, 1996; F-208-3-0-0-2-24
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item24.
    - Simon Fraser monument, October 1911; F-208-3-0-0-2-43
      Donated to SFU Archives by Debra Bodner, Director/Curator of the Nanaimo District Museum. Photograph was originally given to the Nanaimo District Museum by an unknown donor at an unknown date.
      Address:
      Nanaimo District Museum
      100 Cameron Road
      Nanaimo, B.C. V9R 2X1
      phone: 604-753-1821
      fax: 604-753-1777
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item43.
  - Photographs - items 25-34, [19--]; F-208-3-0-0-3 (Archival box - small 208-2)
    - Dedication of historical plaque, October 1972; F-208-3-0-0-3-1
      On Sunday, October 15, 1972, a historical plaque commemorating Simon Fraser, the famous explorer, was unveiled at the site of the Old Fraser Mills, St. Andrews West. This plaque is one of a series being erected throughout the province by the Historical and Museums Branch, Archives of Ontario, acting on the advice of the Archaeological and Historic Sites Board of Ontario.
      Shown left to right after the ceremony are: Mr. Lyall Manson, President, Stormont, Dundas and Glangarry Historical Society; Mr. D. J. McDonald, Reeve, Township of Cornwall; Mr. Robert F. Gray, Vice President, Stormont, Dundas and Glengarry Historical Society; Dr. Simon B. Fraser, who unveiled the plaque; The Reverend John R. Donihee, Parish Priest, St. Andrews West; The Hon. Fern Guindon, Ontario's Minister of Labour; The Hon. Lucien Lamoureux, Speaker of the House of Commons; Professor Keith Johnson, who represented the Province's Historic Sites Board.
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item25.
    - Ann Jane (Fraser) Elcock, [18--]; F-208-3-0-0-3-2
      Photograph donated to Archives by Minnie (Elcock) Biggerstaff, grand-daughter of Ann Jane (Fraser) Elcock.
      Ann Jane was the third child of Simon and Catherine Fraser. Born in 1823 and died in 1854.
      2 copies made by IMC July 24, 1990.
      Negatives available.
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item26.
    - Catherine (MacDonnell) Fraser, [18--]; F-208-3-0-0-3-3
      Photograph donated to Archives by Minnie (Elcock) Biggerstaff, great-grand-daughter of Catherine Fraser.
      Wife of Simon Fraser, born in 1791 and died in 1862.
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item27.
    - Catherine "Kate" Fraser, [18--]; F-208-3-0-0-3-4
      Photograph donated to Archives by Minnie (Elcock) Biggerstaff.
      Catherine "Kate" Fraser was the daughter of Simon William Fraser and grand-daughter of Simon and Catherine Fraser.
      Oversize copy made by IMC July 24, 1990.
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item28.
    - James Fraser, [18--]; F-208-3-0-0-3-5
      James Fraser was the son of Simon William Fraser and grand-son of Simon and Catherine Fraser. Born c. 1850 and died 1908.
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item29.
    - Simon William Fraser, [18--]; F-208-3-0-0-3-6
      Simon William Fraser was the son (1st child) of Simon and Catherine Fraser. Born in 1821 and died in 1896.
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item30.
    - Margaret (Fraser) MacDonald, [18--]; F-208-3-0-0-3-7
      Margaret (Fraser) MacDonald was the daughter of Simon William Fraser and grand-daughter of Simon and Catherine Fraser.
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item31.
    - James Fraser, [18--]; F-208-3-0-0-3-8
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item32.
    - Simon Fraser, [18--]; F-208-3-0-0-3-9
      Simon Fraser was the son of Simon William Fraser and grand-son of Simon and Catherine Fraser. Born 184? and died 1919.
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item33.
    - Simon Fraser (BC Archives, PDP 2258), [19--]; F-208-3-0-0-3-10
      Copy from Provincial Archives of British Columbia, PDP 2258.
      Copyright for photograph remains with Provincial Archives.
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item34.
  - Negatives, 1965 - 1991; F-208-3-0-0-4 (Archival box - small 208-2)
  - Photographic prints (copies) - items 26-33, [19--]; F-208-3-0-0-5 (Archival box - small 208-2)
    Prints created by SFU's Instructional Media Centre (IMC) in July 1990.
- Fraser family artifacts, [19--] - 1995; F-208-4; 2 cm of textual records 2 drawings 4 artifacts 2 textiles
  Series consists of correspondence regarding Fraser family artifacts and includes portrait drawings, a claymore and ceremonial powder horn, a serving platter, bronze profile plaque of Simon Fraser and Fraser Clan hunting and dress tartans.
  - Simon Fraser portrait, [19--]; F-208-4-0-0-0-1
    Graphic materials
    Framed drawing is a copy of a charcoal drawing of explorer Simon Fraser donated to Simon Fraser University in 1965 by his great-great grandson Doanld C. Fraser of Fargo, North Dakota.
    Copy made from original drawing April 1989 by SFU Archives.
    Negative for portrait exists, see F-208-3-0-0-2.
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: D-2-9-3, F-208-item35.
  - Simon Fraser portrait, [19--]; F-208-4-0-0-0-2
    Portrait is a charcoal drawing of explorer Simon Fraser donated to Simon Fraser University in 1965 by his great-great grandson Donald C. Fraser of Fargo, North Dakota.
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: D-2-9-3, F-208-item36.
  - Oval serving platter with Fraser family crest, [19--]; F-208-4-0-0-0-3 (Artifact box - small 208-3)
    Artefacts
    Donated to SFU Archives in 1991 by Lee Lightfoot.
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item37.
  - Powder Horn, [18--]; F-208-4-0-0-0-4 (Artifact box - small 208-4)
    Donated to SFU on September 9, 1965 by Lord Lovat, head of the Fraser Clan.
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item38.
  - Claymore (sword), [18--]; F-208-4-0-0-0-5
    As of January 2006, the claymore remains in the possession of the Office of Ceremonies and Events in their safe. The claymore is used during convocation ceremonies and other university events.
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item39.
  - Fraser hunting tartan, [19--]; F-208-4-0-0-0-6 (Artifact box - small 208-5)
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item40.
  - Bronze profile of Simon Fraser (mounted plaque), [19--]; F-208-4-0-0-0-7
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item41.
  - Fraser dress tartan, [19--?]; F-208-4-0-0-0-8 (Artifact box - small 208-5)
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-208-item42.